[Anthony (Host)] Welcome everybody.
[Anthony (Host)] If I could welcome you to seat.
[Anthony (Host)] We've got some seats up the front.
[Anthony (Host)] You can always grab a chair over there if there isn't quite enough room or sit at one of the tables, but that will mean that you'll be a little bit far away.
[Anthony (Host)] So there's certainly some seats still got a huge influx of interest right at the end.
[Anthony (Host)] So it's great to need extra chairs.
[Anthony (Host)] So I'll just welcome Basil, the patron of the 888 Co-operative Causeway, just to open.
[Basil (Patron)] Right, thank you, Anthony.
[Basil (Patron)] Is it wonderful?
[Basil (Patron)] We have a good crowd here, and I think it's going to be a good energy tonight.
[Basil (Patron)] Anyway, on behalf of Triple 8, welcome.
[Basil (Patron)] And it's good to see you.
[Basil (Patron)] And before I start off, I'd like to acknowledge that we are actually on Indigenous land.
[Basil (Patron)] And I give respect to the elders past, present, and emerging.
[Basil (Patron)] And I'm not going to speak long because Anthony's going to take over.
[Basil (Patron)] But apparently, I've got to tell you where the toilets are in case you need one.
[Basil (Patron)] It's up there past that room there.
[Basil (Patron)] You have a bar, but it's not this one.
[Basil (Patron)] If you need to get a drink, you go to the downstairs.
[Basil (Patron)] And I think that's it, because I think we want to have longer time for the discussions and the questions.
[Basil (Patron)] So once again, welcome.
[Basil (Patron)] And may I introduce Anthony, which I think everyone knows, who is actually the chair of Triple 8.
[Anthony (Host)] Well, thanks everyone for coming along this evening.
[Anthony (Host)] Um, and I'd like to um particularly thank uh uh Designing Open Democracy.
[Anthony (Host)] This is a partnership event.
[Anthony (Host)] Uh we wouldn't have known about the International Day of Democracy if it wasn't for people like Nicholas and Brian, who's also a member of our little cooperative, um, as well as designing open democracy.
[Anthony (Host)] So uh thank you.
[Anthony (Host)] Thank you for that.
[Anthony (Host)] I'd also like to welcome our panelists before we enter into the discussion.
[Anthony (Host)] Um, thank you for being part of this.
[Anthony (Host)] It was all a little bit last moment, so yeah, you you rose to the occasion and we've put together some interesting questions, and then it'll be over to you, which is really exciting.
[Anthony (Host)] So I will just quickly do ah, yes, we have bios.
[Anthony (Host)] So, firstly, um in no particular order, but uh Nicholas Gruen, who is the CEO of Lateral Economics.
[Anthony (Host)] Nicholas is a widely published policy economist and entrepreneur and CEO of lateral economics.
[Anthony (Host)] He has increasingly focused on the deep drivers of political dysfunction.
[Anthony (Host)] Yep, we're going to go there this evening, and on alternative institutions.
[Anthony (Host)] His project, The Shared Centre, explores declining trust in leaders and institutions and proposes ways of putting everyday people back at the centre of decision making, including citizens' assemblies chosen by lot.
[Anthony (Host)] Let's go old school.
[Anthony (Host)] Yeah, that's great.
[Anthony (Host)] And his earlier roles include visiting professor at King's College London, adjunct professor at UTS Business School, and Chair of Kaggle.
[Anthony (Host)] Kagil?
[Anthony (Host)] Kaggle?
[Anthony (Host)] Kaggle.
[Basil (Patron)] Kaggle, owned by Google Now.
[Anthony (Host)] I hadn't heard of Google.
[Anthony (Host)] Kaggle, but yes.
[Anthony (Host)] Googlish now.
[Anthony (Host)] Nicole, welcome.
[Anthony (Host)] Um co-founder and managing director of Mosaic Lab, a really great grassroots organization.
[Anthony (Host)] Nicole is co-founder and an experienced facilitator.
[Anthony (Host)] You're not really watching me too closely, I'm hoping.
[Anthony (Host)] Anyway, specializing in deliberative engagement, strategic planning, and risk communication.
[Anthony (Host)] She has more than 25 years experience across government and private sector projects and led the Yarra Valley Water Citizens Jury, which was very successful.
[Anthony (Host)] She is a fellow and certified trainer at the Engagement Institute and a former board member and co-authored for Stating Deliberation A Practice Guide.
[Anthony (Host)] Cool.
[Anthony (Host)] All right, welcome Nicole.
[Anthony (Host)] And we have Anitra who is part of the inform.
[Anthony (Host)] Formal Urbanism Research Hub at the University of Melbourne.
[Anthony (Host)] Anitra is an activist scholar affiliated with the hub at the university.
[Anthony (Host)] Key recent works include Routledge Hangbook of Degrowth, Beyond Money, a post-capitalist strategy.
[Anthony (Host)] And Anitra and I had some good conversations about horizontalist approaches, which we're going to talk about this evening.
[Anthony (Host)] So I can't wait for that.
[Anthony (Host)] Godfrey is not new to an 888 event.
[Anthony (Host)] I think this is probably your second or
[Basil (Patron)] third time,
[Anthony (Host)] second time around.
[Anthony (Host)] Godfrey is the co-founder of Copower.
[Anthony (Host)] So a little electricity co-op, which I'm a member of, and they're fantastic, and they make decisions very democratically about what to do with surplus.
[Anthony (Host)] We're going to go there.
[Anthony (Host)] So Godfrey is also former executive director at the United Workers' Union.
[Anthony (Host)] And yeah, Copower is a not-for-profit, union-founded, member-owned energy cooperative.
[Anthony (Host)] He chairs Overland Literary Journal and it was written for The Guardian, Overland, Overland, Jacobin, and New Matilda.
[Anthony (Host)] And he has a great substack called The Solidarity Wedge, which I really enjoy reading, and writing on the labor movement strategy and building worker power.
[Anthony (Host)] So welcome everybody.
[Anthony (Host)] All right, well, I have some handy questions prepared to kick things off.
[Anthony (Host)] So where does it all start?
[Anthony (Host)] That's what I'm interested to hear first.
[Anthony (Host)] Because yeah, people like democracy, or they go, or they might feel a bit cynical about it now, but you know, generally people like democracy.
[Anthony (Host)] But you four are really passionate about democracy in your particular way.
[Anthony (Host)] And I'm interested just to kick things off a little bit with that.
[Anthony (Host)] So, um, what drew you personally to democratic ways of living and being?
[Anthony (Host)] And you can talk about personal and or political, home, professionally, uh, anywhere you want to go.
[Anthony (Host)] But um, yeah, where where is where are you personally in relation to uh your commitment to democracy?
[Anthony (Host)] What sort of drives you?
[Anthony (Host)] Um I'm interested in exploring firstly, and we can take turns.
[Anthony (Host)] I might actually go with the person who's closest to me, and you can hand the microphone on.
[Anthony (Host)] What
[Anitra] do you reckon?
[Anitra] Is that democra I I haven't made a democratic decision about that.
[Anthony (Host)] Oh, okay.
[Anthony (Host)] Oh, consensus, does it ever work?
[Anthony (Host)] Anyway,
[Anitra] They've all said yes.
[Anitra] Um well in the 1950s, um, and my dad fought in the Second World War, uh, democracy and freedom were some of the most common concepts that people spoke about publicly, privately, whatever.
[Anitra] And uh the whole war was actually kind of framed as a war over democracy and freedom.
[Anitra] So then in the 1960s, there were a lot of us as teenagers who felt that there were a lot of contradictions and lies in all of that.
[Anitra] So I was pretty much just born into a kind of democracy, freedom, interest in power, power relations.
[Anitra] Um, Australia seemed to be at the arse end of the world.
[Anitra] On television, which came out in the 1950s, you know, it was American, it's still a whole strong British kind of influence in Australia.
[Anitra] Um so power, justice, all of these kinds of things were things that I just seemed to be naturally um attracted to, but were were there and they were there were things that lots of people would engage in.
[Anitra] Um but the probably the greatest um influence on me was um joining a what was effectively a commune, a com a cooperative, a housing um and working cooperative, and finding that uh direct democracy can actually work in practice.
[Anitra] So that was the real hook for me.
[Anitra] I think I'll pass on.
[Nicholas Gruen] Okay, thanks.
[Nicholas Gruen] Um where to start?
[Nicholas Gruen] Um perhaps I'll shock you a little by telling you that if this is the demise if we're talking If by the system, if by democracy you mean the system we have today, this is the system that brought you Donald Trump and Adolf Hitler.
[Nicholas Gruen] So it matters what kind of democracy we have, and there is, I'm not sure of the exact number, but I think it's at least something like 25-30% of younger people are openly wondering whether democracy is such a good thing.
[Nicholas Gruen] And I think that's a basically healthy reaction to the shit show that they see in front of them.
[Nicholas Gruen] So we are at a time, and I think I might kind of harp on about this, I might be the most uh fire and brimstone fire and brimstone among the panel.
[Nicholas Gruen] Uh but we're at a time when extremely powerful people, uh people like Peter Thiel, Elon Musk, and so on, but to think of Peter Thiel, Peter Thiel fancies himself as now Peter Thiel, if you haven't heard of him, is one of he's a billionaire founder, co-founder of PayPal, co-founder of Palantir, the security company, uh, and he's uh an intellectual of sorts.
[Nicholas Gruen] I I mean it's just reasonable to call him an intellectual, uh, and he is the two most important people for him are a person called René Girard, who tells us that we are at the end of times, and Carl Schmitt, who was the premier Nazi jurist in the 30s.
[Nicholas Gruen] Now these people are serious and they're um and they have a lot of power.
[Nicholas Gruen] And my great anxiety is that the people who are supporting things like citizen assemblies and so on, which I think are the best we can, are the best offering we have, um are uh pretty modest in their appetites, pretty modest in their um in what they have to say.
[Nicholas Gruen] They want to start small and iterate and so on.
[Nicholas Gruen] I don't want to be critical of those people, but I want to engineer some kind of collision between the way we are doing democracy at the moment and the way in which citizen assemblies do democracy when they're well well run, because it is very eye-opening.
[Nicholas Gruen] It's really quite an inspirational thing to observe.
[Nicholas Gruen] Uh, and um very few people have seen it, but those who have like the idea of going and talking to politicians and saying, can we do more of this?
[Nicholas Gruen] And the politicians say it's really awfully good of you to spend your time coming and seeing me.
[Nicholas Gruen] And yes, I completely understand where you're coming from, and we'll be trying to do a bit more of that.
[Nicholas Gruen] That's what they said to Martin Luther King.
[Nicholas Gruen] They said, Look, we can't do most of the things you want right now, but um, and please don't embarrass us, uh, but we'll work on it.
[Nicholas Gruen] And it was only when uh the civil rights movement, and the same applied to votes for women, by the way, which were popular in the 19th century, every most thinking people, most reasonable people, most voters thought that was quite a good idea.
[Nicholas Gruen] And nothing happened for decades.
[Nicholas Gruen] But politicians said it was a good idea and so on.
[Nicholas Gruen] And where citizen assemblies and similar things, which we may talk about tonight, where they take place, well, that's no problem for the existing politicians because they're just advisory organizations and they come up with recommendations, and then the politicians have an issues management exercise for a few months, and that's that.
[Nicholas Gruen] So I think we need to think more deeply than that if we want to make any real progress because the people on the other side are very, very serious.
[Nicole] Where did it start for me?
[Nicole] I think is the question.
[Nicole] Um I I'm I guess I'm a really practical person, and for me it started.
[Nicole] I was a government employee for many, many years.
[Nicole] We did lots of different sorts of engagement with lots of different people, and to be really honest, it was really boring.
[Nicole] And and then when I had the opportunity to To see the possibility of a deeper dive approach to something, that's when I thought this has got possibility everywhere.
[Nicole] And when I hear, it's in those little moments when I hear people say, um, I'm gonna call in my ideas to this citizens' jury from the hospital room where my wife's having a baby.
[Nicole] Or I'm gonna participate online during COVID in a citizen's jury whilst I'm having dialysis treatment, or I'm gonna turn up each week in between my cancer treatment.
[Nicole] It's that commitment to something that they believe is bigger than them and that they're making a difference in the world.
[Nicole] That's when the little hairs on my arms go up, and I go, This we could do everywhere.
[Nicole] So that fires a light in my belly, and it's why I do it.
[Godfrey] Cheese pizza.
[Godfrey] That's where uh the sense memory of what democracy beyond the ballot box really came up came for me.
[Godfrey] It was a night out uh with my now wife in in Berkeley in October 2010, where we went to the cheese board collective uh and every evening they do a pizza.
[Godfrey] It's a cheese cooperative, workers cooperative.
[Godfrey] I think it still exists.
[Godfrey] Uh given it was a cheese cooperative, their pizza was a cheese pizza, it was very good.
[Godfrey] I remember the smell, the taste, the delicious beer that went with it, and I thought, you know what, this is a pretty good way of running the world.
[Godfrey] So I'm a bread and roses kind of guy, and sometimes bread can be very persuasive.
[Anthony (Host)] I love a good cheese pizza and I thank you everyone for the you know, telling us all where where you're coming from with democracy and where you see some of the potential landmines that we'll be talking about this evening.
[Anthony (Host)] Uh quite a while back, I saw uh there's a really old bookshop near where I live, and um I'm a bit of a governance nerd.
[Anthony (Host)] I'm interested in that neck of the woods, and there was a vintage book for For the Secretary, um, probably around the 1950s, and the foreword of it says, Now that we have so much more leisure time, and people are getting involved in committees and making decisions and being in the community.
[Anthony (Host)] Here's a great handbook for the secretary.
[Anthony (Host)] It's a very important role.
[Anthony (Host)] It keeps the wheels turning.
[Anthony (Host)] And it just made me think, gosh, you know, like imagine that time when people said, we've got more leisure time, we can get more involved in our community.
[Anthony (Host)] There was some space for that.
[Anthony (Host)] And that was what this really old school book of the secretary told me that this was a this was a different time, in sure, all sorts of factors around um gender and work and all the sorts of things make it complicated.
[Anthony (Host)] But essentially, people were able to be more involved in their community.
[Anthony (Host)] Um there's an app for that.
[Anthony (Host)] We kind of get a little bit individualized, uh, making decisions can be done online using technology.
[Anthony (Host)] Um so I'm just interested if you'd be able to sort of reflect each of you on maybe a little bit about where we've come from and where we could be going and where you see democratic practice going and and the balance, I guess, between does it need to be embodied?
[Anthony (Host)] Do we need to be in person?
[Anthony (Host)] Can technologies help or hinder?
[Anthony (Host)] What's the right balance?
[Anthony (Host)] Wherever you want to go.
[Anthony (Host)] And I might just go in the same order because it's easy to hand the baton on Anitra, unless you'd like me to pass on to somebody else.
[Anthony (Host)] Someone else would like to start.
[Anthony (Host)] I could go a bit rando.
[Anthony (Host)] Um, you just I have to remind me what um quickly.
[Anthony (Host)] We don't have as much time to get involved in stuff.
[Anthony (Host)] Is tech gonna save us?
[Nicholas Gruen] Um I can I draw your attention to something which I suppose I'll call the well maybe I don't know, it's um it's an interesting idea that democracy requires us all to be involved.
[Nicholas Gruen] We should all have the option to be involved.
[Nicholas Gruen] That's true.
[Nicholas Gruen] But there's something a bit fantastical about the idea that we are all involved.
[Nicholas Gruen] And a contrast to that is there is a democratic institution that we don't involve ourselves in, but we have a lot of faith in it, and that's called the jury.
[Nicholas Gruen] And the jury will come up with an answer, and we typically often there is a lot of aggro in our public sphere about the outcome of court cases, but very little aggro towards citizens.
[Nicholas Gruen] And when we hear of a verdict, we think there, but for the grace of God, go aye.
[Nicholas Gruen] Those are ordinary people, and a very large majority of them, I think, and someone may be able to correct me, but I think in Victoria it's nine out of twelve, have come to a particular conclusion.
[Nicholas Gruen] And that's okay for me.
[Nicholas Gruen] And so I think there is something somehow mistaken in the idea that a democracy involves that there's a sort of an image, it's not explicitly said, but there's a sort of an image in which everyone's involved in everything.
[Nicholas Gruen] And it's obvious that that's wrong.
[Nicholas Gruen] Uh there needs to be a division of labor.
[Nicholas Gruen] And so we've been sold this kind of a populist idea of democracy that we should all be involved in everything, and there's just a kind of cacophony all directed at the media.
[Nicholas Gruen] And what I want, you know, I don't ever want to go to a meeting about how garbage is collected in my neighborhood.
[Nicholas Gruen] I will go if it's part of my democratic duty, but I don't want any more people than necessary to go to sort that thing out.
[Nicholas Gruen] And there are a million things that governments do.
[Nicholas Gruen] So what I want is I want some confidence that something's happened, now we're only collecting garbage once every two weeks or something.
[Nicholas Gruen] And I want there to be some, I want to have some faith that that decision, whether I agree with it or not, was reasonably made.
[Nicholas Gruen] And mostly we don't have that sense because we have a politician yapping at us with some uh talking points, and then we have some inane journalists trying to trip them up, and then we have the opposition saying it's all terrible, but if they were in government, they'd be saying what the government's saying, and the current government would be saying what the opposition is saying.
[Nicholas Gruen] So it's a complete panto, and it's and people can see that that is not worthy of them.
[Nicholas Gruen] Um and so, yeah, that's my contribution to that.
[Nicholas Gruen] That yes, a democracy does need an involved citizenry, it needs a virtuous citizenry to some extent.
[Nicholas Gruen] But it doesn't, it absolutely doesn't mean that we all have to be busily um, you know, watching all the current affairs shows and all that sort of stuff.
[Nicholas Gruen] Um I'll just leave you with a thought um by a guy uh called Pope and his son Hugh Pope.
[Nicholas Gruen] I'm telling you like this because I've forgotten the Christian name of the man who wrote the book, but his son Hugh published this book, he found it.
[Nicholas Gruen] Um and and he quotes um G.K.
[Nicholas Gruen] Chesterton saying that democracy is about giving the shy people as much of a say as the blowhards like me.
[Nicholas Gruen] I'll pass on.
[Nicole] I think your question was, will tech save us?
[Nicole] Um I think my view is no.
[Nicole] But it's it's also gonna it's also gonna help and hinder.
[Nicole] That would be my view.
[Nicole] I think that we have we are in an environment that means we are going, we can have conversations across the seas online with each other in real time and not have to fly everyone around the world.
[Nicole] Um, we can and we can that helps, that's technology.
[Nicole] But it's not gonna save us.
[Nicole] Like um, no matter whether we use AI or we're using an app or we're doing a survey or we're using some polis or whatever it is we're doing, all of those, all of those technologies, any technology, be it a method in a room, will exclude people and include people.
[Nicole] So, you know, it's a it's a suite of things we've got to Include.
[Nicole] And I think we've got to think carefully about the barriers at every point.
[Nicole] I totally agree with Nicholas that not everybody has to be involved in every conversation and we need to think carefully about methodology to do that.
[Nicole] I also think we are at a serious turning point with technology.
[Nicole] The news today is an example of that.
[Nicole] There are many people, and I have watched a so-called deliberation at a global level that's been run by Meta that's completely automated.
[Nicole] There are people from around the world, it is an automated task, you get a time, you fill out a thing, you move on, you go on to the next task, and you watch it in the background, and it is terrifying in my eyes.
[Nicole] Because there is no meeting of the minds.
[Nicole] They are ticking off boxes and moving through a process.
[Nicole] And the context we're in now is we have to understand difference.
[Nicole] Take time to sit and talk to people who think differently to us, otherwise, we will tribalize more and more and more.
[Nicole] And social media is just amplifying that at the moment.
[Nicole] So we just need to be really careful with any technology we're using to support the process.
[Godfrey] I think Samuel Johnson wrote, Reason dies alone.
[Godfrey] And the issue with technology is that it displaces social cooperation, which is kind of bizarre in the sense that the technology only exists because of that pre-existing social cooperation.
[Godfrey] And we can see that when people try and think of solutions in the public discourse.
[Godfrey] You mentioned it before, Anthony.
[Godfrey] There's an app for that.
[Godfrey] So often now we think what's the technical solution, what's the technological solution?
[Godfrey] And there's not a discussion or a discourse about what is the structural or organizational solution that we need to bring to bear on that.
[Godfrey] So we've we've we got organized enough to create this technology and now it's preventing us in a way from reorganizing in response to changed facts and changed circumstances.
[Godfrey] And I think that is that is the issue that technology has a place, but we've got to get the prior question of organization done firstly.
[Godfrey] And the other factor in relation to that is time.
[Godfrey] We just capitalism has found a way to take and rob us of time, whether it's through the smartphones that we're addicted to in our pocket or or trying to find the next gig or job or whatever else it is.
[Godfrey] And we need a way of fighting for shorter working hours, but in a in a way that means that people can live a life that is economically secure and have the time so that participation is not bounded by privilege.
[Anitra] I'm not sure whether I've got anything extra to add to that.
[Anitra] Yeah.
[Anthony (Host)] Nothing wrong with a bit of economy.
[Anthony (Host)] No, thank you.
[Anthony (Host)] And yeah, so I've I do have a question though for you, Anitra.
[Anthony (Host)] Um so you work on this thing called degrowth, which may not be familiar to everybody.
[Anthony (Host)] Um, and you talked a little bit about being a part of collaborative housing.
[Anthony (Host)] Um and yeah, housing's a really tricky area.
[Anthony (Host)] I've done work in that neck of the woods, and and everyone, well not everyone, but some might have an experience of a thing called an owner's corporation, um, body corporate.
[Anthony (Host)] So yeah, it's a it's a tricky area when people are making decisions around their living arrangements and how they live together, whether it's in close quarters or even just talking about common infrastructure like a block of flats, and then if you're renting, you just cut out of that altogether.
[Anthony (Host)] But um yeah, there's you've also talked a lot about being less dependent on this thing called money.
[Anthony (Host)] Um, and you know, back in the 90s it was, you know, use your money as your vote, these sorts of things were being said.
[Anthony (Host)] So um I'm wondering whether from your experience and um your interest in this sort of more horizontal decision making, um if you can see some indicators for where we can best go in such a divided and polarized world, which we've we've started to talk about, and the relationship between that.
[Anthony (Host)] And the way we use money, you know, like um often those two things we talk about making decisions together as if this thing called money doesn't exist out of it.
[Anthony (Host)] So I'm really interested in your thoughts because you've looked at those deeply, how those two things are connected and where we can maybe go.
[Anitra] Yeah, okay.
[Anitra] I became really interested in this.
[Anitra] Um, in my undergraduate years, I did Latin American studies and uh I was doing a history major and decided that in fact Latin American history and the Australian history that I was aware of really boiled down to economic history, and so that's what really drew me into economics.
[Anitra] And um I ended up doing a PhD on Karl Marx's concept of money.
[Anitra] Um so uh by that time, um, and I'd had a long involvement in both environmental movement as well as women's movement, and women's movement has a lot of horizontalism, which I can come back to, but that was my introduction to horizontalism, having assemblies and working groups and people really self-organizing, a lot of self-governance.
[Anitra] The kind of position that I'd come to was that we have all these big social problems of inequities between people, and we have growing in ecological crises, and every time that we look at these, examine these kind of problems, people seem to come back to economic conundrums.
[Anitra] Um if you take monetary relationships out of the picture, um it can be it can solve a few problems.
[Anitra] So, number one, inequities can regenerate it within society.
[Anitra] One of the reasons that I think that it's been really difficult for the women's movement to move has been that okay, you can give people opportunities when they're in their 30s or their forties or whatever.
[Anitra] Um, but the elite, the the patriarchy, as it were, still has is so far ahead that, and because the way that money works and investments and accumulation, um any group that's actually given an opportunity is only kind of like going to make very slow progress.
[Anitra] So I recognize that monetary economies very much generate and make more complex all of the inequities within societies.
[Anitra] Money is about more and less.
[Anitra] It's about competition between that.
[Anitra] That's the whole dynamic of it.
[Anitra] Um, in terms of ecology, um the biggest problems that we kind of face now today is sort of like Australia is in a position where the average Australian is producing andor consuming at the rate of there being about five Earths.
[Anitra] We really have to be all collectively making decisions about our futures, which means that we get back on track.
[Anitra] We have to do that collectively.
[Anitra] We actually have to be more democratic.
[Anitra] There's no bigger kind of um process or organizational challenge than that as I see it today.
[Anitra] So I can talk about horizontalism and stuff later, but yeah.
[Anitra] Yeah.
[Anthony (Host)] So just as a little follow-up, because uh in the co-opi neck of the woods, um there's uh uh essay from the 1970s women's movement that I came across through the work of Nathan Schneider, who's um quite active in the cooperative movement globally.
[Anthony (Host)] And it was interesting this this essay called The Tyranny of Structurelessness by Jo Freeman talks about her experience in the 1970s of being in these um feminine collectives that looked very, very flat, and she's really excited and got into.
[Anthony (Host)] Involved in them.
[Anthony (Host)] And then after a little while I sort of realized actually there's people making decisions here, but I don't actually know how they're making decisions and who the decision makers are.
[Anthony (Host)] So she started to talk about the importance of structure.
[Anthony (Host)] So when you talk about something like horizontalism, it might sound like choose your own adventure and have a bit of a scrum.
[Anthony (Host)] Whereas what Jo Freeman was saying, that you need to be really clear about who's doing what and who's accountable.
[Anthony (Host)] So I'm just wondering if, on a sort of a practical level, whether you'd be able to comment on that.
[Anitra] Well, it's very similar because a lot of people misrepresent anarchy as being chaos or just complete freedom.
[Anitra] Anyone does whatever they like.
[Anitra] And it's not like that at all.
[Anitra] Anarchy is really self-governance.
[Anitra] And you have to have processes and they have to be transparent and everything has to be accountable.
[Anitra] So when I lived in a commune, we had a meeting every Monday morning, and we divided up all the tasks that needed to be done through the week for both the kind of enterprise that the commune partly lived off, and all of the more self collectively self-sufficient kind of growing vegetables, looking after children, all of those kinds of housework jobs and all of that kind of thing.
[Anitra] And that's direct democracy.
[Anitra] That's you know, and we I mean, it wasn't as if people just decided that they'd do any old job and that they'd work when they felt like it at all.
[Anitra] It was like we had set rules over what kind of work was work, what kind of activities weren't work.
[Anitra] Um so uh I think that probably in the last 50 years there's been a lot more clarity over um structure in that sense.
[Anitra] And for me, I can't see much structure in the worlds of Boris Johnson, Donald Trump, and all of these kind of mainstream democracy.
[Anitra] I can't see a structure like that's really scary, and you know, it seems to be a little bit like the kind of structuralistness argument that people get at.
[Anitra] And what that structuralist argument is really getting at is that under certain circumstances, when people aren't treated as if they're equal and there's just an equal space for them to speak and act and have power over people, well then there's a really big problem.
[Anitra] And that's what we've got a lot of the time within capitalism and capitalist politics.
[Anthony (Host)] Yes, flooding the zone, so we're just um thinking that everyone's having a say, but really um it's just a lot of crap, really, um, where we're at.
[Anthony (Host)] But we're trying to get out of the crap a bit, and I'm looking across at Nicole.
[Anthony (Host)] Um, so we've gone from Commune, so I'm gonna go to the Yarra Valley Water Citizens Jury because that's a really practical um grassroots process that you were involved with, um, and heard lots of fantastic things about it.
[Anthony (Host)] Now, this is where so-called ordinary people come together and talk about water and try to make decisions.
[Anthony (Host)] Could I really fascinated in terms of how that actually works.
[Nicole] I could talk for three weeks on this, so I'll be really quick.
[Nicole] So, um, first and foremost, it is a random selection of people from the community, or in this case the customer base for Yarra Valley Water, stratified against what that community is like.
[Nicole] So it's a mini version of the customers in the room.
[Nicole] So age, gender, location, uh could be background, depending on whatever the filters might be.
[Nicole] So we randomly select two-stage random selection to get a group of people in the room that represents their customer base.
[Nicole] And then we spend a lot of time with them, um, at least 30% of the time.
[Nicole] And in the case of Yarra Valley Water, uh, there's a couple of times we've been through this, we spend at least six days all together.
[Nicole] Half of that time is learning.
[Nicole] Learn, learn, learn, learn, learn, understand, dialogue, ask questions, pick your own speakers, um, uh really to interrogate what this.
[Nicole] Thing is, which is how much does our water cost?
[Nicole] And then you take time throwing up ideas on we agree with this, this should be the way it should be priced, we think this is most important.
[Nicole] You make decisions, they write their own the report, they hand it over.
[Nicole] The organization then says we will include this to the maximum extent possible in our price submission to the regulator.
[Nicole] So that's it in a nutshell.
[Nicole] There's obviously lots of parts to that, lots of ins and outs.
[Nicole] And one of the biggest bits, the most enjoyable bits, is seeing the transformation from the beginning to the end.
[Nicole] Most people who come in in these processes are unknown to the organization because of the random selection.
[Nicole] And for me, that is the biggest change in the way we engage with our communities because it's nicer to get an invitation than to just, you know, turn up to the things you normally.
[Nicole] You know, if you get an invitation to a party, you're more likely to go.
[Nicole] But if there was just a notification of a party, you're not going to go to it.
[Nicole] So that makes a difference.
[Nicole] Pardon me.
[Nicole] Um, the second bit is we spend a lot of time on brain biases.
[Nicole] How do we naturally bias our thinking?
[Nicole] Therefore, how do we do critical thinking differently?
[Nicole] And how do we elevate that in the way we live and work, and particularly in this situation?
[Nicole] And last but not least, they make decisions, they that write the report.
[Nicole] There's not a report given to them that's blank.
[Nicole] And to hear the sorts of things you hear at the end of a process like this, I have run hundreds of these things, but at the end of it, you hear people say, you know, this has changed my life.
[Nicole] I've had people sign up to these things for the money.
[Nicole] I had one woman, I'll tell her story because it's beautiful, it was for an energy organization.
[Nicole] This woman signed up because she needed to get her teeth done.
[Nicole] So she signed up to get the money because you pay people a stipend, it's minimum wage to be in the room, which I think is fair enough.
[Nicole] They give a fair amount of time.
[Nicole] Oh my god, she was the best participant I've ever had.
[Nicole] She struggled with every single concept.
[Nicole] She did the homework, she turned up, she challenged everyone in the room, and they got a really good result.
[Nicole] And she is an advocate for that organization to this day because it changed her life.
[Nicole] And I kid you not, just about at every closing session I run for a deliberative process, I cry.
[Nicole] I'm that emotional, because you see the shift in people.
[Nicole] They are like, I can make a difference.
[Nicole] I am powerful.
[Nicole] I've worked with others.
[Nicole] This is a great thing.
[Nicole] We could do more of this.
[Nicole] This is how it works.
[Nicole] And they say, and they say, and this is democracy.
[Nicholas Gruen] Not not the not the 730 report with Sarah Ferguson trying to trap whoever she's trying to trap that night.
[Nicole] And it's the it's they're really diverse, right?
[Nicole] These people are really different and have very different views on the world.
[Nicole] And they come to a meeting of the minds because you take the time, you slow it down, you learn about stuff, you talk to each other, you meet people who are different to you.
[Anthony (Host)] Well, speaking of energy, Godfrey, uh you are a co-founder of Co-Power, uh, and members of that cooperative uh and people associated with it make decisions about what happens with some of the surplus.
[Anthony (Host)] So it's an interesting democratic um enterprise that it's dealing with money that Anitra's been talking about, and it's dealing with actually doing, you know, making decisions together about what's done with it.
[Anthony (Host)] You'll you've also recently finished with um United Workers Union.
[Anthony (Host)] Uh, you've written in your Substack about members in unions being part of the decision-making process and some of the challenges around that.
[Anthony (Host)] So you've been involved in doing something about decision making, and and um you've also been involved in the union movement.
[Anthony (Host)] So I'm interested in the dialogue between those two things and whether you want to have a more of a discussion about how maybe unions can be a little bit more democratic and how co-ops could fit into it.
[Anthony (Host)] Wherever you want to go with it, Godfrey.
[Godfrey] Thanks.
[Godfrey] Um so what I would say about Co-Power is we uh Tom and a few other comrades, we we set it up as an intervention in the market to try and eat the market and and return value back to the commons.
[Godfrey] It's a big ambition, we've got a very long way to go in relation to that.
[Godfrey] But um we I think this this issue about money and elections is really important and the work that Nicole's talked about in uh citizens' assemblies and water authorities, because we thought there was an opportunity with Copower because of how privatized and corporatized, at least in Victoria, the retail end of the electricity market had become.
[Godfrey] You see your electricity company on the television, you are literally paying for that on your bills.
[Godfrey] It might not be expressly itemized in your bills, but it's an allowable charge that retailers can pass on.
[Godfrey] So when we're talking about the resources that it would take in order to transition our energy systems over to something that is at least a lot more sustainable into the future.
[Godfrey] When you see a billboard, when you see a TV ad or something else, you are seeing resources being spread around in a vastly inefficient manner, money being spread around in a vastly inefficient manner.
[Godfrey] And that's the system that we're in.
[Godfrey] If you read Aristotle's politics, elections weren't in the section on democracy.
[Godfrey] Elections were in the section on oligarchy.
[Godfrey] Because it was an institution that was, uh, in Aristotle's view, uh best suited to those who had the most amount of money.
[Godfrey] And the only way through that is how do we build systems of direct democracy, which requires structure and organization.
[Godfrey] And I've spent most of my working life thinking through how do we get people organized and spend far too little of my working life thinking through what does that organization look like at the end, which I think is a vital question for a vital question for our age, because the labor movement is in crisis.
[Godfrey] We do have an issue there about uh workers being alienated from the labor movement, being distant because of its entanglement in parliamentary politics and inherently oligarchic systems of parliamentary elections, which is part of the pre-existing um lack of confidence, I think, within the movement to build power in the workplace, build power within everyday communities.
[Godfrey] Uh and I won't go into you know, I've I've written quite a bit on that.
[Godfrey] We could have a whole uh TED talk on it, but what I would say, yeah.
[Godfrey] Yeah, fair enough.
[Godfrey] Um what I would say is this one thing that we need to divest ourselves of in authorities.
[Godfrey] I think most of us walk around with a mental model in our in our head around authority of top-down structures, and those top-down structures uh exist in a vacuum or maybe on like a billiard board table when really we're all nested within subsystems and systems and broader systems and ecosystems.
[Godfrey] And we need to get that Western capitalist mindset out of our out of our head, which is probably an overhang from the Catholic Church and the Roman Empire, with you know King Charles up on the wall there.
[Godfrey] Hierarchy structure isn't dependent on hierarchy.
[Godfrey] Authority shouldn't be dependent on hierarchy.
[Godfrey] I think the best leadership and best authority exists when it exists on the border between systems, where you have people, structures, and collectives that act as translators between needs of various systems, whether it's the ecosystem and the village, whether it's um whether it's an enterprise and and an industry, whether it's a local community and a broader uh ecosystem or like a river delta community.
[Godfrey] We need to think through authority as about people existing on borders and bringing that knowledge and communication channel for more deliberative structures and um and direct participation in place.
[Anthony (Host)] So Nicholas, I had uh some questions about citizens' juries.
[Anthony (Host)] We've already sort of gone there a little bit, um, and I think I think Godfrey raised some really interesting things, and I thought, oh gee, maybe maybe Nicholas might want to respond to some of the things that Godfrey's just said there around the nature of democracy, or you might want to dig deeper into um the idea of these um citizens' juries and how kind of you've already outlined how kind of toxic representative democracies become, and I think you know you just have to watch TV to agree with that.
[Anthony (Host)] So yeah, I'm interested in Yeah, where you want to go, you might want to respond to some of the things that other panelists have have mentioned.
[Anthony (Host)] Um, and you might want to dig deep into the citizens' juries, or yeah, just generally the economics of the thing.
[Nicholas Gruen] Uh no, I won't talk about the economics of it.
[Nicholas Gruen] Um, but I will take you up on the on um following on from Godfrey.
[Nicholas Gruen] I was very pleased that Godfrey mentioned my close personal friend Aristotle.
[Nicholas Gruen] Um, and Aristotle, as he rightly said, described elections as aristocratic or oligarchic.
[Nicholas Gruen] Oligarchic now, Aristotle's three forms of government uh exist in a good form and a bad form.
[Nicholas Gruen] And the bad form is always when the people in power make it about themselves rather than about the public.
[Nicholas Gruen] And that can happen to a kingship, which becomes a tyranny, it can happen to an aristocracy, which then becomes an oligarchy, and it can happen to a democracy, which then becomes what he called an ochlocracy, the rule of the worst.
[Nicholas Gruen] Now, the other thing that Aristotle said, he didn't just say that elections were naturally aristocratic or oligarchic.
[Nicholas Gruen] Let's understand why he said that.
[Nicholas Gruen] Oligarchy is the rule by the few.
[Nicholas Gruen] And if you hold an election, that's what you're trying to do.
[Nicholas Gruen] You're trying to get the consent of the many to choose a few who will govern them.
[Nicholas Gruen] There are all kinds of ways in which that's absolutely necessary for social functioning, and there was an Italian-German theorist of the turn of the 20th century called Robert Michels, who coined the expression the iron law of oligarchy.
[Nicholas Gruen] And he showed how as organizations become more complex, you can't spend all your time going back to plenaries the whole time.
[Nicholas Gruen] You have to have structures.
[Nicholas Gruen] And I think Anitra was saying something a little bit similar, and that article about uh that you referred to is similar.
[Nicholas Gruen] So, what do elections do?
[Nicholas Gruen] They separate the governed from the governing.
[Nicholas Gruen] They are competitive by definition.
[Nicholas Gruen] And Aristotle said something that I thought think is really sublime about this alternative in uh institution, which is selection by lot, by lottery.
[Nicholas Gruen] Um he said that that is an that is uh a quintessentially democratic uh institution, and it involves people taking turns in governing and being governed, which is exactly what happens in juries.
[Nicholas Gruen] And so it doesn't separate the governed from the governing except in so far as is absolutely necessary.
[Nicholas Gruen] It doesn't disturb the essential equality of people while accepting that there is a division of cognitive labor in any complex situation.
[Nicholas Gruen] Somebody has to be on that jury, twelve people have to be on that jury, and they have to sit through twelve days or whatever it is, and then they deliberate on that.
[Nicholas Gruen] And it's completely absurd to have a hundred people doing it or everyone doing it, although that's kind of what we do at the same time for our own entertainment through the press.
[Nicholas Gruen] So these very simple ways of thinking about the structures that govern us have really influenced me very strongly because I do think that, I mean, Anthony let the expression drop just a minute ago.
[Nicholas Gruen] He talked about representative democracy as if that meant elections.
[Nicholas Gruen] No, it can, you can talk about representative democracy and everyone does, as if that presupposes elections, but it could presuppose the alternative way to represent the people, which is what happens in juries.
[Nicholas Gruen] Representation by sampling rather than representation by elections, with all of the profound differences that that involves to equality, to the framing of what's going on.
[Nicholas Gruen] If you set up a competition, you'll get a certain kind of discussion.
[Nicholas Gruen] And we can see it every day because not only is our political system um profoundly competitive, but the medium through which it travels to us, the media, has always been competitive and is now much more competitive than it was.
[Nicholas Gruen] And it's more or Less doing to our political system what happens to a fly when you spray morteen on it, which is that you dissolve its nervous system.
[Nicholas Gruen] Just dead.
[Nicholas Gruen] So that's a bunch of thoughts.
[Nicholas Gruen] I'll just say one other thing, which is that Nicole spoke, well, about the tears in her eyes, I know what she means.
[Nicholas Gruen] She spoke about the fact that you can't run one of these exercises well, which Nicole does, without producing the kind of transformation in the people that she mentioned.
[Nicholas Gruen] And the way I put that is that we evolved on the African savannah to do that.
[Nicholas Gruen] And when people discover it, it completely astonishes them.
[Nicholas Gruen] And I wouldn't be going on about democracy so much if I just thought this was a terribly hard problem.
[Nicholas Gruen] It's not that hard.
[Nicholas Gruen] Because this other way to represent the people just sits there, and every opportunity it's given performs in an astonishing way, if you get it all close to it.
[Nicholas Gruen] But we don't, so it would be with the there is more than enough philanthropic money around for us to set up a standing citizen assembly of a hundred odd people that simply shadowed the federal parliament.
[Nicholas Gruen] No, don't ask for any permission.
[Nicholas Gruen] Just run it, turn people over every six months or two years or whatever you decide.
[Nicholas Gruen] I've got a few ideas about how you ultimately create a situation where it could become self-governing in the way that the House of Representatives or the Senate are, these are self-sovereign bodies that make their own decisions and generate their own tradition and go through their own history and their own crises and have their old hands who can help the newcomers and so on.
[Nicholas Gruen] So, anyway, that's what I think.
[Nicholas Gruen] I think we could I think, I mean, there are so many problems of human life where you come up with a really hard problem andor a really ingrained problem, and you basically don't really know how to solve it.
[Nicholas Gruen] You've got a few clues and you try some things out, but this, I don't think, I can't prove this to you, but I don't think that's one of these problems.
[Nicholas Gruen] I think the answer is staring us in the face.
[Nicholas Gruen] And it would be like passing through a portal.
[Nicholas Gruen] Um so that's what we can do, but nobody will.
[Nicholas Gruen] I can't do it because I don't have $10 million.
[Nicholas Gruen] Um and the people who do have all that money run little display shows here and there, and they go and talk to politicians, and the politicians say how good it is of them to do this stuff, and they say, you know, I had this great meeting with senior politician, and and it was really, really good, wasn't it?
[Nicholas Gruen] Okay, yeah, yeah.
[Nicholas Gruen] It was very like the meetings you had 15 years ago.
[Nicholas Gruen] Anyway, I'll leave it there.
[Anthony (Host)] Well, I've got one more question before we hand the mic across to you all.
[Anthony (Host)] So if you're holding some questions, um getting some questions together, um, that's coming next.
[Anthony (Host)] But yeah, I just wanted to finish this part of things with a little bit more of a question to you, Nicole.
[Anthony (Host)] Um, because what Nicholas was saying sort of prompted me to think about, you know, you get this decision-making process where people are chosen by lot.
[Anthony (Host)] I think that's a really exciting idea.
[Anthony (Host)] Um, one of my favorite quotes is from a theologian Kallistos where he says that simply that we need to learn to be free.
[Anthony (Host)] So freedom's just not some automatic thing, there's there's a learning to be free.
[Anthony (Host)] Um, and so the processes that you undertake, we talked a little bit about it um ahead of this evening.
[Anthony (Host)] You talked about, to me, this uh way of education and and learning about the subject.
[Anthony (Host)] So these people are chosen by lot.
[Anthony (Host)] How does that learning happen?
[Anthony (Host)] How does it happen in a way that doesn't sort of bias things too much?
[Anthony (Host)] And we talked a bit about the tyranny of structurelessness.
[Anthony (Host)] So these people are chosen by lot, they're learning about the topic, and then there's a way of facilitating that conversation in a way.
[Anthony (Host)] So I'm interested in a little bit more of the nuts and bolts of how to learn to be free.
[Nicholas Gruen] Easy questions.
[Nicole] Okay, so um first things first, there's uh the experts because we're all experts, the experts for that topic.
[Nicole] There's a lot of I'd say there's a lot of work we do as practitioners to get them ready to be in the room to let go control.
[Nicole] Because that's really important that they're ready to go sort of hand the batten over.
[Nicole] I mean they're there as a resource, but they're not involved in that conversation.
[Nicole] We we put strict guidance around that.
[Nicole] At the moment, you're an observer.
[Nicole] So that means you sit over there and they're doing their stuff.
[Nicole] You're not influencing them.
[Nicole] So that's one part of the process.
[Nicole] For the participants themselves, it's a slow build, right?
[Nicole] You're starting with um getting them working together, understanding that their experience with this, how do you work together to make decisions?
[Nicole] How do you how do you experience that normally?
[Nicole] How might we do it in this room?
[Nicole] Critical thinking bias.
[Nicole] I talked about that before.
[Nicole] Then when you're getting into topic-specific stuff, we do a lot of learning in really small groups, like pairs and threes, and then build, build, build, build, build to a whole group.
[Nicole] We do things called speed dialogue.
[Nicole] It's like speed dating, but better.
[Nicole] And uh it means that they're in small groups with a person who knows a bit more about this from the organization, maybe, maybe from outside the organization, and they sit and have small conversations, and then that person shifts to a new group.
[Nicole] And you just take your time to talk about it and learn about it and unpack information.
[Nicole] You use um, we'll read a little bit and share it with each other and learn from a pack of information.
[Nicole] It's sort of like a slow build from the start, the basics to kind of like becoming really knowledgeable and starting to weigh up trade-offs.
[Nicole] Like we'll go into a conversation that's about, well, you know, you could go this way and it has these risks and benefits, and we could go that way and it has those risks and benefits, and they start to weigh it up.
[Nicole] So you'll literally do whole group conversations like, so how do you feel?
[Nicole] Like, would you stand on this side?
[Nicole] I'd stand over here and half the group over there, and let's have a conversation about that.
[Nicole] So you can see how it's it's built so many little tools in there from individual thinking to pairs to threes to the whole group to kind of dialoguing and trading off, and all of that builds to them, then going, now what do we think is the answer to this collectively?
[Nicole] And we build that up together as well.
[Nicole] And in fact, that moment of choosing what solutions we think are to this problem and building it together for me is the most sacred part of a whole deliberation because that is like the turning point where they go from me to we and they go from that to I understand that, and I understand what you mean by that when you say that, and there are people in the world who are saying, Yeah, we could get AI to do that for us, they could just theme up their ideas, and I'm like, uh-uh, don't touch it, because that choice making the group is doing at that moment has them really understand what they're saying and owning it.
[Anthony (Host)] Well, I don't know about you.
[Anthony (Host)] I got really inspired then.
[Anthony (Host)] So, yeah, that's just that's very exciting.
[Anthony (Host)] Um so thank you, panelists, for answering some of these questions.
[Anthony (Host)] But now it's over to you, um, and I might go over there and hand to Nicholas.
[Audience Q1] So yeah, I wonder before um Nicole, you were mentioning something about um any sort of technological process or any process is going to include or exclude people.
[Audience Q1] And um, Anitra, you mentioned that you know we're burning through like five earths at the moment, the way consumption goes.
[Audience Q1] Uh I'm just thinking though, um any process that we would formulate now, it's only ever going to include you know living people like us.
[Audience Q1] It's not gonna include future generations or animals or anything.
[Audience Q1] Um, and so you see, like people they don't like voting for austerity.
[Audience Q1] So, you know, no matter how sort of democratic a process is, I think Anitra, you were saying we need more democracy in order to solve the problem of burning through five earths.
[Audience Q1] Um, I'm inclined to think that no matter who we select, uh, especially if it's like random juries, aren't we going to end up with people who just keep voting in their own current self-interest against future generations?
[Nicole] It's a great question.
[Nicole] Um, I will say that there are processes we run, depending on the conversation we're having, that is about bringing in the future voice as best we can.
[Nicole] So this has been done a lot in Japan.
[Nicole] Japan, where they'll literally say, We're gonna, there's gonna be a group of you, and we're gonna collectively decide who they are.
[Nicole] Let's say there's five of you, and your job every time we do a process is to act like you're the future, or to act like you're the trees, or to so to to actually bring in voices.
[Nicole] I'm not saying it's perfect, but there are processes that are trying to do that so it's not just coming from my current needs, my current approach.
[Nicole] I totally think it's a real dilemma to think forward and to bring that in.
[Nicole] And I think there are micro processes we can do that might support that.
[Anitra] Yeah, I'd just say that um already to begin with, if you frame questions around the fact that you want to live a one planet lifestyle, well then you've you've already started to think about the future because you're talking about sustainable reproduction.
[Anitra] So I think it's the way that you frame those questions that helps you address future generations having all of the opportunities that they might expect to have.
[Nicholas Gruen] There's something else I think that's worth thinking about, which is that we have been conditioned for for a long time now to think of our vote as we are participants in a market, we are competing with each other in some kind of sense.
[Nicholas Gruen] Now it's quite interesting.
[Nicholas Gruen] I hadn't thought about this, but uh the uh the uh political philosopher Hannah Arendt talks about the secret ballot.
[Nicholas Gruen] Now, the secret, I'm not gonna tell you that the secret ballot's a bad idea, but it is an idea that leans heavily on the idea of privacy and therefore of the individual rather than the res publica, that we get our term republic from the idea the Roman expression the public thing.
[Nicholas Gruen] So republics, and this was big in the minds of the founding fathers in the United States, the to sustain a republic, you need people to be thinking of the public thing.
[Nicholas Gruen] And unfortunately, our more and more our elections are framed around what is in it for me.
[Nicholas Gruen] That's how the media will report on a tax package or anything like that.
[Nicholas Gruen] Uh, and if I know that I'm going into uh I'm going into here I am adopting that sort of language, if I know that I'm going into vote against people who want to uh uh just go with coal-fired power and all the rest of it, I'll be trying to vote against them.
[Nicholas Gruen] It's kind of me versus them.
[Nicholas Gruen] So um but but again, and and I didn't really I did advert to it a bit, but the whole business of being in a citizen jury is that you're not saying who's got 51% of the votes here.
[Nicholas Gruen] You think you're saying what can we live with?
[Nicholas Gruen] And that doesn't mean unanimity.
[Nicholas Gruen] I think Nicole can correct me, but there's a sort of a folk wisdom among many people who they go for 80% majorities.
[Nicholas Gruen] I'd I'd be happy with less than that.
[Nicholas Gruen] But uh, well, you sort of start for 80%, and and no doubt Nicole's had some interesting questions about around that mark, you know, that particular whatever arbitrary mark you pick.
[Nicholas Gruen] But the point is that the psychology of that, the theatrical framing of that, is not a vote out.
[Nicholas Gruen] It's not I'm gonna go and log roll as many votes as I can get, we'll go away for two weeks and I'll be on the phone and I'll be trying to get 51% of these votes.
[Nicholas Gruen] That isn't how human beings relate to each other.
[Godfrey] I think um capitalism gives democracy a bad name.
[Godfrey] Right, when you're talking about how um people might not vote for uh degradation to their quality of life, well, that is about how we try and scrabble around and make a living within a system that just is a is is an undead vampire on the planet.
[Godfrey] And the good life isn't a ready-made meal, the good life isn't getting stuck in traffic, the good life isn't always feeling so freaking tired.
[Godfrey] People pay a lot of money to be able to go on a very exclusive trip to Italy or retire to a place like that when what makes part That a good life is is the local wine or the produce or the time that people can spend together.
[Godfrey] We need to rescue democracy and the good life from a system that is ultimately parasitic upon our present now as well as our future.
[Godfrey] And uh more and more of us are are feeling that.
[Godfrey] Because I I sure as hell is not I'm hoping that my kids' future is not just some other commodity, because that's just deep and depressing.
[Audience Q2] Thank you.
[Audience Q2] I've got a question for Anitra in relation to her expert view on degrowth.
[Audience Q2] How does it play out in the power realm that we're talking about?
[Audience Q2] And how do you apply it personally?
[Audience Q2] Like, do you live in a tiny house?
[Audience Q2] How do you negotiate degrowth?
[Audience Q2] How do you apply it in Melbourne?
[Audience Q2] It's something that as urban planners we're all grappling with.
[Anitra] Great, thank you.
[Anitra] Um okay, so it's a really big topic.
[Anitra] But um degrowth did the degrowth movement basically evolved to address those two big questions of growing inequalities and ecological unsustainabilities.
[Anitra] And degrowth has always had a really strong democratizing principle involved with it.
[Anitra] And there are lots of um different ways in which uh degrowth um is applied.
[Anitra] So the um the handbook that um I co-edited with Vincent Liegey has about 35 chapters, um, but really it's just a tiny segment.
[Anitra] Um, and lots of people are addressing degrowth in a whole variety of different ways depending on which country they live in or whatever.
[Anitra] Um so the general kind of framework, I'll sort of stick to the democracy as a kind of through line in it.
[Anitra] The democracy um part of it um has basically flourished into a general consensus over our futures being commoning, that there's um that we actually let go of private property, that people actually acknowledge that they're just passing through earth and handing it on to other people, but also other animals, other plants, and so that that whole sharing, caring, cooperative way of approaching everything is the way that commoning is instrumentalized, okay?
[Anitra] Using a lot of the kind of ideas of assemblies and having working groups that are enacting these things.
[Anitra] At the basis of it, it's essential that we we're actually living as modestly as we can, but also as convivially as we can.
[Anitra] In other words, just loving one another's company, um, actually getting a lot of creative nourishment ourselves out of thinking around problems of using less materials and energy to do things.
[Anitra] Um I could keep on going, but I'm just aware that we've got you know more.
[Anitra] Yeah.
[Anitra] Um in terms of Australia and trying to and trying to do degrowth, there um is D-Growth Network Australia, which meets um online um different parts of Australia every month.
[Anitra] There's a NAM DG Growth, um, and NAM DGrowth does really great things like have festivals at Ceres with a lot of like groups like Well Being Alliance and the kinds of policy.
[Anitra] I would say, or programs, or whatever that degrowth follow, are things like universal basic services being applied so that everyone has immediate access to basic services, but there's a limit on it.
[Anitra] You were talking about tiny houses, yeah.
[Anitra] So really the uh in Australia in planning and stuff, we've um often had kind of like minimums for sizes of housing and number of bedrooms before we call it overcrowding and all that kind of thing.
[Anitra] Well, DGrowth turns that on its head and says that we need to have the maximum amount of space that people occupy.
[Anitra] And uh also uh I mean we've done a there is a sort of housing for degrowth book which sort of goes through a lot of that that the planning, but another kind of edge on all of that is decentralization, so that we actually don't live in cities that are sort of cocoons away from nature and seeing how things are grown and how animals are killed and all of that kind of thing.
[Anitra] But rather we're really close and all of us involved with growing our own food.
[Anitra] Um also kind of speaking earlier with someone who's been in Nepal where people are readily all together make their own houses, repair their own houses, all of that kind of thing.
[Anitra] So there's a lot more of doing it together and planning that's kind of most of the planning regulations and building regulations are all created for industry and people are actually not allowed to do stuff, and what we need is again to turn that on its head and have enabling policies so that people can always with the um modification that you want, safety and security, but um people being involved in building their own houses, in growing their own food, and that kind of thing.
[Anthony (Host)] That's fascinating.
[Anthony (Host)] Sorry.
[Anthony (Host)] Pardon my um
[Audience Q3] thank you very much to all four of you for for sharing what democracy could be and and your experiences with that.
[Audience Q3] What I miss now is that we begin to talk about the urgency of how we change things because you talked about uh democracy gave us Hitler, democracy gave us Trump.
[Audience Q3] In Germany two weeks ago, democracy gave us alternative for Deutschland, which is a party with close affiliations with neo-Nazis, with Russia.
[Audience Q3] And and the world keeps changing.
[Audience Q3] Democracy has given us one nation.
[Audience Q3] So, how do we move from sitting in a fringe corner talking about what democracy could look like theoretically into something about the something urgent and something about the how, how do we do it.
[Nicholas Gruen] Well, um my suggestion is that uh we persuade uh we make some donations ourselves, but we try to persuade uh philanthropists with the money.
[Nicholas Gruen] It's not that expensive, maybe two million to run a citizen assembly for six months to a year, uh, and then to fundraise on the back of that.
[Nicholas Gruen] And basically to run and and my point about the point my point in suggesting this is that people need to see this hap they need to see this thing working.
[Nicholas Gruen] Um and they need to see that it they need to feel their own agency and the way in which um it can make better decisions in certain circumstances than the people they see in front of them.
[Nicholas Gruen] I don't know, I mean, probably most Australians don't know that much about AUKUS, but it's a kind of a joke.
[Nicholas Gruen] It's just a sort of mad exercise where Scott Morrison signed up to this thing.
[Nicholas Gruen] I wasn't that farcical at that stage.
[Nicholas Gruen] The Labour Party, as far as I can see, signed up to it because they didn't want the election to be about that.
[Nicholas Gruen] And then, a bit like Tony Abbott, who won election by getting rid of carbon pricing, and somehow couldn't understand that he then needed to somehow replicate something a bit like a carbon price because otherwise things would look more and more farcical.
[Nicholas Gruen] So anyway, the Labour Party didn't take this opportunity.
[Nicholas Gruen] They didn't get into power and say, I'm shocked, I'm shocked that more work hasn't been done on this and we can't go ahead with this.
[Nicholas Gruen] There are just oodles of these things.
[Nicholas Gruen] So that's one of the things that a standing citizen assembly could be doing.
[Nicholas Gruen] So I'm my idea is to try to organize collisions between the way we're doing politics now and another way of doing politics.
[Nicholas Gruen] Now that isn't, I mean, the these people have no formal power, but we still live in an open society.
[Nicholas Gruen] They still can have a big impact.
[Nicholas Gruen] I think if we had had a body like this in 2013, Tony Abbott would have found it very difficult to get the abolition of carbon pricing through the Senate because it wasn't actually that easy for him.
[Nicholas Gruen] It was only a few votes.
[Nicholas Gruen] And if you have 60 odd percent, 65% of Australians, random Australians, ordinary Australians, figuring out that this makes no sense.
[Nicholas Gruen] Just by the way, we are paying $12 billion more tax every year than we would have if we hadn't abolished carbon pricing.
[Nicholas Gruen] The revenue from the carbon pricing was going to rise inexorably.
[Nicholas Gruen] I hadn't done the calculations lately, it may be $15 billion.
[Nicholas Gruen] They would have figured that out.
[Nicholas Gruen] They would have said to the people who wanted to get rid of a carbon price, right, so we're going to be on the hook to pay this much more revenue.
[Nicholas Gruen] In other words, Tony Abbott would have had more, a bigger challenge on his hands than getting through a 10-minute radio interview, which was all he had to do.
[Nicholas Gruen] That's the system.
[Nicholas Gruen] So that's what I suggest.
[Nicholas Gruen] And I'm I think that having another citizen assembly in an era, I mean, the some of the things that Nicole's talking about is rather different because Yarra Valley Water citizen assemblies are sponsored by Yarra Valley Water, and they're trying to build a system that has some social license and social buy-in.
[Nicholas Gruen] That's different to say Mr.
[Nicholas Gruen] Macron's, oh God, what or for that matter, Julia Gillard's, oh my God, what do I do?
[Nicholas Gruen] I know I'll have a citizen assembly and that'll diffuse the situation, and then a year goes by, and then that everyone's got the same dilemma.
[Nicholas Gruen] I'm more sympathetic.
[Nicholas Gruen] I'm not telling you this story on the basis that Emmanuel Macron is a bad guy.
[Nicholas Gruen] He's facing a bunch of incentives.
[Nicholas Gruen] And he thinks a citizen assembly will be a good idea, and then he looks at lots of the recommendations and he thinks I can't go to an election and win if I've done those things.
[Nicholas Gruen] So that's so with kind of charity for all, if I can quote Abraham Lincoln, we can build ways in which people see these things.
[Nicholas Gruen] And what I'm hoping is that if people become familiar with this, then minority parties like the Teals and so on might win their choosing between governments.
[Nicholas Gruen] So I ran round the corridors of Parliament coming up to the last election thinking that the Teals might have the balance of power, how wrong I was.
[Nicholas Gruen] But had they had the balance of power, I was saying to them, you should say that one of your demands, if you you can say to Albo and say to Dutton, first thing on my auction is a standing citizen assembly.
[Nicholas Gruen] You don't have to promise to do anything, just have a standing citizen assembly.
[Nicholas Gruen] Well, they weren't close to doing that.
[Nicholas Gruen] Um, so there's a lot of socialization to do, a lot of familiarity to do.
[Nicholas Gruen] I'll leave it there.
[Godfrey] Um I was just gonna say, I think the a lot of my work with the Solidarity Wedge is about how do we have a radical labour movement strategy that meets the moment.
[Godfrey] Uh and it's actually not that hard.
[Godfrey] Anyone can do it if you if you think through the the parameters, but What I've rubbed up against is that uh even from a position of relative privilege within the Labour movement, that that just died.
[Godfrey] Like it it didn't go anywhere.
[Godfrey] And I think the reason why it didn't go anywhere is because in order to be able to do that, you need to radically change the balance of internal power between uh exec like labor movement leaders like I was, uh, no longer, and rank and file delegates and organizers and the operational autonomy that they would have.
[Godfrey] And that's an incredibly threatening proposition.
[Godfrey] And so I've rapidly came to the idea that, well, there is a cybernetic question here about organizational design and what sort of organizations do we build that are fit for purpose to meet the moment that we're that we are in.
[Godfrey] And I know it's way more complex than this, but I look at the the uh rise of the the radical right uh and their their increase in popularity as symptomatic of the moment that we're in, that it's almost as if people in this quite atomized, alienated times are feeling, whether it's not a sense of belonging, whether it's a material uh issue or insecurity or whatever else it is, uh, a sense of frustration with the system, and there is a flashing red button that they can hit, and that flashing red button here is one nation, and then AFT elsewhere, and Trump, and so on, and so forth.
[Godfrey] And the solution has to be what is it that is not just that flashing red button?
[Godfrey] Because it's a very uh coarse way of doing it, but it's also a brilliant systemic intervention on the system as it is, because you push the flashing red button to express your frustration, and then really what you're doing is just reinforcing the existing, the existing structures within the system.
[Godfrey] So it's this like brilliantly designed negative feedback loop to reinforce what we have.
[Godfrey] And we've got a people need something else that they can do, anything else.
[Anitra] Um I think that it's a trap to think that um the political realm is where the where the decisions are being made.
[Anitra] The biggest decisions that are being made in the system that we live in are being made by capitalists.
[Anitra] And this is one, this is at the base of the problem of us not being able to confront climate change and all of these kinds of things.
[Anitra] Politicians have very little power.
[Anitra] It's the people who have the money that invest in um big projects who are making the decisions.
[Anitra] Recently there's been a lot of media coverage of the data centers.
[Anitra] And um the conversation uh had an article, I think it was either this this morning or yesterday, on trying to answer the nine big questions that people had about data centers.
[Anitra] Number one question: how come we never knew it was going to happen?
[Anitra] Well, we don't know things are going to happen because we're never involved, and the politicians aren't involved with what our futures are going to be.
[Anitra] Capitalists decide that.
[Anitra] They're the ones who are out there deciding, well, we'll use this technology, we'll do this, that, and the other.
[Anitra] And it's the fifth anniversary of AUKUS, actually, um, today.
[Anitra] Okay.
[Anitra] Um really good example of all of that as well.
[Anitra] A lot of what AUKUS is going to do is to put money in certain people's pockets, and it's also going to make us feel more terrified and feel more disciplined and feel less powerful, and as if we can do and say something, we're the ones who actually have to decide that yes, it is urgent, and we're going to have to break the rules of this society in order to change things.
[Anitra] You can't have change if you don't have change.
[Anthony (Host)] I reckon we've got two more questions.
[Anthony (Host)] I did have uh sorry to take over, but I'll just throw over to you.
[Audience Q4] Good evening.
[Audience Q4] Thank you, panelists.
[Audience Q4] It's so nice to hear people reflect on this idea that actually we're can we we're innately good at this.
[Audience Q4] We are equipped like inherently equipped for the challenges of our time because we are innately.
[Audience Q4] I think it's really interesting the $10 million you threw out at to start with around what it would cost to set up a standing citizen jury.
[Audience Q4] And the pivot yeah,
[Unclear/Crosstalk] (inaudible – audience quip)
[Audience Q4] like... I see.
[Audience Q4] Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[Audience Q4] Fantastic.
[Audience Q4] And then I'm kind of interested to go, all right, the um community forums that worked really well for Yarra Valley Water, they did they happen like whether they happened in person or online?
[Audience Q4] And I'm hearing what you're saying also around this that Standing Citizen Assembly might shadow federal government.
[Audience Q4] I spent a lot of time in China in the last little while and have been reading about their mission economies and going, actually, in 2000 there was a plan that said we're going to move towards, or the CPC said we're moving towards ecological civilization, because it's a good idea and we're all and there's lots of problems within that, but this is the a thing that we want to move towards.
[Audience Q4] And I'm wondering a couple of things.
[Audience Q4] Would the standing, I think the two million dollars is an easy target to get, and I think that if we were going to set up when when we set up a standing citizen assembly or something that is like that, and the examples that are present in Taiwan is really ringing in my mind, is to say, would it be enough?
[Audience Q4] I think what I've heard is that we need there to be a flashing red button that people can respond to.
[Audience Q4] So it would need to have broad-based support in terms of the flashing red button that we anyone in Australia can hit to engage in this process needs to be there.
[Audience Q4] Would should the thing that gets the the first citizen assembly the first standing citizen assembly that Australia runs, should should the focus of it be shadowing the like a government process as it is now?
[Audience Q4] Or should it be, we know that there is like international precedent for setting, making decisions together.
[Audience Q4] Should it be something broader?
[Audience Q4] Like should it be a vision setting citizens' assembly that says, actually, we're gonna probably some of us will be alive in 80 years' time, what does that Australia look like?
[Audience Q4] I wonder if, yeah.
[Audience Q4] So my question is, does the when we do the first standing citizen assembly in whichever form it is, does it, should it be more broad strokes?
[Audience Q4] And what would be the what would be the smaller things that we would need to what would be the smaller citizens' assemblies that we would need to run before we get to like the federal level?
[Audience Q4] That's a really big question, but yeah.
[Nicholas Gruen] I'm not arguing for starting small.
[Nicholas Gruen] I'm saying we go to a standing citizen, federal citizen assembly.
[Nicholas Gruen] Um you ask what should it focus on, I'm going to ask the Citizen Assembly.
[Nicholas Gruen] The idea that I want it to, I mean, I will try to put in its mind a simple idea from economics called opportunity cost.
[Nicholas Gruen] And that was um that was immortalized in the words of the Spice Girls.
[Nicholas Gruen] Tell me what you want, what you really, really want.
[Nicholas Gruen] But the point is that they've got to make a decision about where they focus because they can't focus on everything.
[Nicholas Gruen] And that would take a while, uh, and it would take uh a lot of you know, they would learn a lot, you know, they might be spending more time learning than than Nicole's Yarra Valley Water outfit, but that's the idea.
[Nicholas Gruen] It's not, it's absolutely not an idea of starting small.
[Nicholas Gruen] That is the opiate of activists everywhere.
[Nicholas Gruen] Um it's it's not revolutionary, you see.
[Nicholas Gruen] I call this incremental radicalism.
[Nicholas Gruen] And what I mean by that, it's well, it's it's kind of strangely countercultural.
[Nicholas Gruen] But we have this idea that if you have if you think radically differently, you want a revolution or you you want all sorts of stuff.
[Nicholas Gruen] My view is that I've given you all a little bit of an idea of how profoundly different the logic of a citizen assembly is and how it is also democratic.
[Nicholas Gruen] It is, and we're very familiar with it, we're familiar with juries.
[Nicholas Gruen] So, what I mean by radical incrementalism is that you put, you know, like a bit of ink in a bit of water, you have a body that operates according to a different institutional logic.
[Nicholas Gruen] They have so in Michigan, they have the Michigan Independent Citizens Redistricting Commission.
[Nicholas Gruen] They had gerrymanders for generations, and a girl, I think her name might have been Nicole, uh, got on Facebook and said, let's have, let's pass a citizen-initiated referendum.
[Nicholas Gruen] And now 13 randomly selected, it's a bit more complicated than that, but uh I won't go into the detail, but essentially 13 randomly selected Michigan citizens redraw electoral boundaries.
[Nicholas Gruen] And here's the amazing thing um it wasn't always the case in the United States, usually Democrats.
[Nicholas Gruen] Ran gerrymanders and they did it in the South.
[Nicholas Gruen] And what the Democrats, you know, the Democrats can go and hang their head in shame about what they got up to in the South.
[Nicholas Gruen] But today, gerrymanders assist Republicans in a big way, and Donald Trump's been trying to crank up the Republican gerrymander before the midterms.
[Nicholas Gruen] So the majority of Republican politicians vote for Republican gerrymanders, otherwise, they wouldn't get up, because I can tell you Democrat politicians vote against them.
[Nicholas Gruen] But if you poll American citizens, if you poll a Democrat citizen and you say, do you think gerrymandering is wrong or very wrong, 92% of Democrats say that it is.
[Nicholas Gruen] And if you poll Republicans, 88% of them say that it is.
[Nicholas Gruen] So if you build the right kind of institution, you can tap into the public's sense of, hey, we're a democracy, I'm going to defend my democracy.
[Nicholas Gruen] But they're not going to defend democracy so that one group can lie to them instead of their favorite, you know, instead of the politician who is channeling their anger.
[Nicholas Gruen] They want their anger expressed, and I can fully understand that.
[Nicholas Gruen] Did I win over time?
[Anthony (Host)] Well, it's been a great conversation, and there were some great questions.
[Anthony (Host)] And there is still food here, and there is still a bar downstairs, and uh we have each other, and some of the panel members will, I'm sure, uh stick around for the conversation.
[Anthony (Host)] As is our tradition, we uh finish every little 888 event uh with our patron, Basil, to just do a it'll have to be a little shorter than usual, reflection on what we've heard.
[Anthony (Host)] Um, and yeah, Basil has really supported our cooperative, it's just in the center of town.
[Anthony (Host)] We have a little shared office space, little co-working space.
[Anthony (Host)] It's democratically run, it's voluntary, and we run events here.
[Anthony (Host)] So if you'd like to talk to me or any of my 888 colleagues about that afterwards, we're happy to have that chat with you.
[Anthony (Host)] Uh, but yeah, let's just close with some reflections from you, Basil, and I can give you this mic, or you can go up to the lecture and ever, however, you want to do it.
[Basil (Patron)] I'll get up because I need to
[Basil (Patron)] get up.
[Basil (Patron)] This uh
[Basil (Patron)] reflection is going to be very difficult because it's been a great contribution by four, I think, marvelous people who actually believe in democracy.
[Basil (Patron)] They might have different interpretations of it, but they actually believe in it.
[Basil (Patron)] And that belief is actually very important, and it's very complex with that belief.
[Basil (Patron)] Uh, my my reflection is that democracy.
[Basil (Patron)] I mean, I'm glad people talked about Aristotle, who happens to be one of my favorite philosophers, but
[Basil (Patron)] limited, I might dare say.
[Basil (Patron)] Because it's limited because it's predominantly a Western mind.
[Basil (Patron)] So it still hasn't come to terms with Indian philosophy or even Chinese philosophy.
[Basil (Patron)] The other thing I liked about was a question, I don't know your name, but you said that democracy has produced such hideous, awful characters and has dragged people into it.
[Basil (Patron)] I think Germany is a very good example.
[Basil (Patron)] So much so that they even banned the notion of actually talking about anti-Semitism.
[Basil (Patron)] And that has a reaction.
[Basil (Patron)] But what I would like to say is that maybe I'll end up in I've been given instructions by the chair to speak very short time.
[Basil (Patron)] I was I must share this because at the age of six, I was with my grandfather, and he took me to the family well.
[Basil (Patron)] Incidentally, I come from a state called Kerala, which people may have heard, but it is actually God's own country.
[Basil (Patron)] Because we elected a communist government, a Marxist government.
[Basil (Patron)] We have actually done marvelous things, but I don't want to be culturally chauvinistic.
[Basil (Patron)] So, but anyway, so I'll just relate to the fact of my grandfather.
[Basil (Patron)] And he took me to the family well, because in those days we didn't.
[Basil (Patron)] Not have plumbing for the house.
[Basil (Patron)] It was
[Basil (Patron)] water was just from the well.
[Basil (Patron)] And it was a wall, and
[Basil (Patron)] he asked me to look
[Basil (Patron)] down.
[Basil (Patron)] And I looked and I said, Oh, I can only see the water.
[Basil (Patron)] He said, with his voice a bit more grumpy.
[Basil (Patron)] He said, No, have a proper look.
[Basil (Patron)] And I
[Basil (Patron)] had a look, and there was a little green frog.
[Basil (Patron)] And I said, There's a little green frog.
[Basil (Patron)] And then my Achachan, as I used to call him, said, You know, that little green frog is very happy.
[Basil (Patron)] And I said to him, In that case, Achachan, I want to be a little green frog.
[Basil (Patron)] And I remember his face and he smiled.
[Basil (Patron)] And then he said to me, No, that's very good, but just remember, your task in life is to climb out of the well and come there and have a look.
[Basil (Patron)] And you see, and that frog will see the whole sky.
[Basil (Patron)] And if life gives you that opportunity, you will see other green frogs coming out of their wells.
[Basil (Patron)] And tonight we have had four people coming out of their wells and creating and croaking, and now hopefully creating great song.
[Basil (Patron)] My question, because I'm really, this is very important for me.
[Basil (Patron)] I've been an activist since 1964.
[Basil (Patron)] I can remember when Aboriginal people were not even given the vote.
[Basil (Patron)] I can remember my struggle against apartheid.
[Basil (Patron)] I can remember the gender, which I had to come to terms as a man.
[Basil (Patron)] What is it for women to be truly equal?
[Basil (Patron)] I know a lot of men now just say, yes, they're equal, but have they really gone through it and held what is it actually to what is it to be culturally chauvinist?
[Basil (Patron)] Now, why is this important?
[Basil (Patron)] Because I think this is where democracy actually happens.
[Basil (Patron)] It is when people want to live their lives in good company, reasonably comfortable, and enjoy the good life.
[Basil (Patron)] And when we deprive people of that, we have problems.
[Basil (Patron)] And therefore, I would say, as a suggestion, we have a great start here.
[Basil (Patron)] Let's pool our thinking, our resources, and take some of the learnings that they've given us tonight.
[Basil (Patron)] And let us create great song so that we can actually turn the tides of people like Pauline Hanson and One Nation.
[Basil (Patron)] So let's do it.
[Basil (Patron)] Thank you.
[Anthony (Host)] That's beautiful, Basil.
[Anthony (Host)] And thanks to our four green frogs.
[Anthony (Host)] You've sung a lovely song this evening for all of us.
[Anthony (Host)] Now, this is a voluntary run thing.
[Anthony (Host)] We did.